We're finishing up Tzadi Hei about Nosen Ta'am Lifgam. Okay, so we touched about it a few times. We talked about the soaps and things like that, Nosen Ta'am Lifgam, not being Nosen Ta'am Lifgam necessarily lechatchila. Okay, if you look in the Shulchan Aruch in Tzadi Hei Dalet, if you look in the Shulchan Aruch Tzadi Hei Dalet, I'm going to try to go fast and see if we can get through the end of Tzadi Hei. If not, we'll have to wrap it up next week. It's some straightforward
stuff. Okay, so the Shulchan Aruch says in Tzadi Hei Dalet, Yeira Li, which is always an interesting thing when the Shulchan Aruch says ירא לי שנתן אפר במים if a person puts ash into the vat of water, במים חמין שביורה קודם שהניח הקדרות בתוכו before he puts anything in, אף על פי שהשומן דבוק בהן even if, so he puts ash into a vat of
water before washing let's say dirty milchig and fleishig dishes together, even if there's stuff on top, mutar says the Shulchan Aruch, that would be mutar, דעל ידי האפר הוי נותן טעם לפגם. The ash is Nosen Ta'am Lifgam so I put something in that is some kind of, you know, of, okay, some kind of detergent and it makes it bad so it's lifgam and everything would be mutar even if there was stuff on top of the
plates. Why... why... hold on one second, one second, one second, let me just let's get through a little bit. If you go to the Shach, so the Shach says where in the world did you get this from? This is not a Gemara, there's not a Gemara in Chulin, there's not a Gemara anywhere. Where did you get this from? So the Shach in Sif... this is why by the way now you have to realize that the Shach, the Shach does not live that much after the Shulchan Aruch. The Shulchan Aruch is the 14th, the 1500s. The Shach is the 1500s. The Shach, you know, is 1600s,
I'm sorry. The Shach is not רב שלמה זלמן אויערבאך in the 2000s or the 1900s, but nonetheless the Shach, his level that he would argue with the Shulchan Aruch because he was that level. Rabbi Kinach would tell us that there are certain Gedolim, certain Acharonim that could argue with Rishonim, Akiva Eiger, the Shach, certainly things like that. So if you look in the Shach, the Shach says where's this come from? Where's it come from? Says דין זה לא נמצא בשום פוסק. Okay, this is not found anywhere. ולא שום אחד מהאחרונים הזכירו גם
בבית יוסף לא הזכירו, not only that, you Shulchan Aruch didn't mention this in the Beis Yosef. So not only that, he goes through, if you go to the next line, he quotes a Tosafos that not only that, but there's a Tosafos in Chulin that seems to go against this Gemara, that essentially it goes against this Gemara because he quotes a Tosafos and he quotes a Rosh, we'll say it outside, but והרא\"ש ופירוש רבינו אפרים דאמרינן דנתעסקו בו אלא רק בשר וחלב הניחו מה שצוותה התורה
להגעיל כלי מדין. We know that in Parshas Matos we learn about all the ideas of hagala. So the Tosafos, the Gemara says היכי הכשירו יורה גדולה, I'm sorry, the Shach, היכי הכשירו יורה גדולה, one second, says the Shach. Whenever hagala is needed, so hagala performed on a, right? We perform hagala, everything seems to be clean. Tosafos says how
could hagala ever be effective? Why? He says היכי הכשירו יורה גדולה והלא המים שישם כנגד והמים נותנים טעם פירוש הניחו כי לא נעשו המים כולו נבילה. What happens? You could only perform hagala on keilim that did not have shishim in them. Meaning, anytime I put hot water in a kli to do hagala, it re-awakens anything that was inside there. So it would always be a problem. So, says the
Tosafos, if you keep reading, if you look up this Tosafos in Chulin, so Tosafos says that it must be that they were only, that if the kli was large enough, there wasn't shishim that it would be okay. So the Shach says at the last line ואם איתא הלא התורה לא בא ללמוד אלא להגעיל כל אחד כדינו ומשום מים יוסר היאך תקנת הדבר. All they had to do in Klei Midyan was to do what? Throw some ash in. The Torah never mentions this idea.
Shach says it can't be that this is a real thing. This is a real thing. Tosafos says, based on the Shach, that really you should be able to kasher large ben yomo keilim. That means they were used for treifus today and I throw something in there. Obviously we don't do that, and therefore this halacha is made up. So there are other poskim that agree with the Shach, that this halacha is not found anywhere. You're telling me that I could take a massive, a massive pot, I could throw soap in there, then I could put in keilim and put in milk and put in fleishig. It doesn't, it doesn't make sense, how could you do that? So that's what the Shach
says. So the question is, who's right? Shulchan Aruch says it meforash. The Shach says it's not true. Hold on one second, hold on one second. No, no. Yireh li means you could do it. Yireh li doesn't mean like I think it's a good idea. Yireh li means you could do it. Yireh li probably means that it's not brought down anywhere, but I think you could do it. So when does he say yireh li? It's a very... it's a strange lashon. Yireh li usually comes from the fact that it's not a meforash Gemara, it's not a meforash. The sevara makes good sense. The sevara makes good sense. So now, if you look in the Chacham Tzvi, there's
a... there's a Taz. There is a Taz in se'if katan tet-vav, we're not going to do... there is a Taz here that quotes a Maharshal that also says it's a problem. There is a Gra here. If you look in the Be'ur HaGra, right below the Shach, below the Nekudas HaKesef, there's a Gra. The Gra on yireh li says עיין ט\"ז וש\"ך שחולקים על זה. So the Gra also seems... the Gra is not like telling you, \"Hey, you should look at the Shach, and if you figure out the Shach, this is what he says.\" The Gra's saying that because
the Gra says that I hold like the Shach and Taz. Okay. So if you look in the Chachmas Tzvi... the Chacham Tzvi, depends on how you like to pronounce it. If you look in the Chacham Tzvi, the following: says מה שכתב הש\"ך דין זה לא נמצא בשום פוסק ואינו כלום ומה צורך לכתבו כמבואר בגמרא ובכל הפוסקים שכל נותן טעם לפגם מותר. He explains that what does it mean that no one ever paskened this way? דין זה
לא נמצא בשום פוסק. That we know that that applies. We have this concept. What's that concept called? Nosen ta'am l'fgam. So it doesn't mean nosen ta'am l'fgam doesn't apply. What does the Shach mean that this halacha doesn't apply? The ash. Meaning, that's yireh li. Yireh li... so what's the makor? So he continues, and he explains that the machlokes really here is arguing is that
the... he says ואפילו אינו פגום גדול דומיא דקדירה שאינה בת יומה שאינו פגום אלא מעט יותר מבת יומה. The Gemara says that after 24 hours, what happens with the taste? The absorbed flavor is pagum, and it can no longer forbid things. The Shulchan Aruch takes that halacha and he extrapolates that halacha and he says that's even true if it was a ben yomo. Because I know that eino ben yomo works and after 24 hours something becomes pagum and it becomes bad. So therefore, yireh li that if I could take a ben yomo kli,
I could throw ash inside and poof, I got a situation of ta'am l'fgam. I don't care that there's ta'am in the walls of the pot because when the ta'am comes out from the walls of the pot, it has a fight with ash and everybody, everybody should be okay. Okay? So hold on one second. And therefore, don't bring me this whole Tosafos because even Tosafos would agree that you can kasher ben yomo by being pogem the pot. Tosafos, in fact, if you look at the end of the Chachmas Tzvi,
he says all Tosafos was saying... don't bring me a raya from Tosafos that Tosafos doesn't bring this issue what they did in the midbar in against Midian. Why? Tosafos was quoting you one thing that they did. That doesn't mean you couldn't do other things. It wasn't an exhaustive list. Tosafos wasn't telling you all the ways to kasher the kelim. Tosafos was saying when you have big pots it wouldn't work אלא חדא מתרתי או תלת נקט. Tosafos was presenting one method of kashering kelim, that smaller kelim and things like that, but there'd be no reason,
says the Chachmas Tzvi, that you would not be able to kasher a kli by putting in afar. Now, the Chazon Ish in source 54... so that's the Chachmas Tzvi that seems to say that the Shach is actually not arguing... the Shach is not arguing against the Shulchan Aruch, they're really just arguing on ash. Okay? Okay. So if you look in source 54 in the Chazon Ish. Says the Chazon Ish: מהוכיח הש\"ך שאין העפר פוגם את המים. When you told... when you
mentioned that they agree that, you know, it's... that it's pogem the water... that the afar's not pogem the water אלא מים נעכרים בעירוב העפר. That's when the adding substances are genuinely pogem something. But they disagree really just about ash. They're just arguing about ash. ומה היש בדורותינו מיני חמצן. But today when we have real bleach and things that are mamash pogem, they're not arguing. They would agree.
They would agree if I threw in something that's very, very bad. Why... what's the issue with ash? Why would ash be different? It's not bad enough. It's not bad enough. And he says potentially also the ash floats to the top, it's not as me'urav and everything. Okay, so they're arguing about ash itself but they're not really arguing... Maybe that's what they used back in those days. Is the...
Correct, right. So they're arguing whether or not that works or not. That's what the Chazon Ish says. Okay. So the l'maise we should never really what what should we do? So if you look in source fifty-five, if you look in source fifty-five, okay, all we should really do today when you call the rabbi and you say, \"Rabbi, was this did I kosher did I traif up this pot?\" The rabbi says \"yes\" because we get a kickback from the hagala, okay. Why do we need all of this? Why do we need all
of this? What should I do? Put in soap. Put in just take take a plate, pour some bleach on top of it, shain, everything's good, we're good to go, okay. So the Badei Hashulchan in source fifty-five says the following: אבל אם לא נתן האפר במים אלא אחר שנתן בו הקדירה that the leniency of nosein taam lifgam is only when the pogem substance is added before.
שנתן בו אחר שכבר נבלע בשר בחלב בדופני הכלים לא מהני אפר לפגום מה שבלוע בכלי That only works if I add the thing in and then what? That things get mixed together. But once the forbidden flavor has been absorbed, adding bleach isn't going to do anything, right? Adding bleach won't do anything. So l'maise, potentially you could fill up a massive vat, huge pot, dump tons of bleach in, and wash your milchig and flaishig dishes together, okay. If you... What? Well so this means you cannot
have you cannot just have one dishwasher. Oh, hold on wait wait we're not at dishwashers yet, hold on a second, hold on a second. So now if you go to one more source on this topic, if you go to source fifty-six, l'maise how do we pasken? So in the end we seem to we don't really know that ash will ruin it, but in source fifty-six the Chachmas Adam says כל זה שכתבנו בהדחה שעושה דוקא במדיח מים נקיים אבל נתנו אפר במים חמים but he
says if you put it in hot water, קודם שידיח הכלים אף על פי שהשומן דבוק מותר דהאפר נותן טעם לפגם the Chachmas Adam seems to pasken that it would be good to go. I can throw things I can throw some kind of bad detergent in, some kind of bleach in, wash all my keilim and everything should be fine. The the Badei Hashulchan though, I'm sorry, yes, in source fifty-seven, that you really shouldn't just lechatchila. והני מילי בדיעבד שכבר נתנו
הקדירות בתוכו אבל לכתחילה אין להניח במים דלכתחילה נגמר ההיתר דנותן טעם לפגם You have to realize that to do this is essentially saying that I'm relying lechatchila nosein taam lifgam, that I'm throwing in tons of bleach, I'm putting milchig dishes and flaishig dishes while it might be okay bidieved it would not be the best idea lechatchila and therefore that is really how we pasken. So if you take one takeaway from tonight it should not be that you go home and say we don't need dishwashers, we can throw tons of bleach and put everything together. We're going to talk about soon in a second dishwashers
where Rav Ovadia is like wildly lenient on things, but don't worry, Ashkenazim we got it, we got it, we got it. Yeah. What about the Badei Hashulchan? Yeah. And he doesn't like putting in efer once it's already mixed in. But why? If I put whatever pogem substance, bleach, soap, whatever it is, into the pot and then I boil the water with that, why wouldn't that draw out whatever taam that's in the walls of the pot, mix that, make it pogum, whatever goes back in
is pogum? I lost you Jules halfway through. One more time? Sorry. Okay, the Badei Hashulchan says that if it's already mixed in the walls of the pot... One second. A bleach is not mivla from the walls of the pot. No, no, no, I'm saying. That's what... So when if I make a if I have a traif pot, I traifed it up, meatballs. Fine. It's mamash traif. Mamash traif. The Badei Hashulchan says if you put the pogum stuff in, you're not doing anything. Correct.
According to the Badei Hashulchan, what if I put a bunch of pogum stuff in and boil the water, whatever that stuff, together? Why doesn't that why doesn't that go into the walls of the pot and counteract the stuff that's in the pot? No, I'm saying, it seems to me it would either draw it out like a reverse a reverse hagala. Well, it's I'm saying it's part of that. Like if you do that first, it would seem to make it pogum. That sounds super bidieved. I can say it wasn't bidieved, I'm saying even according to the Badei Hashulchan... One second, that's how we kosher in general though, why are you making it so complicated? That's
how we kosher. Of course, but it's not a ben yomo. I'm saying why wouldn't it... Oh, a ben yomo. Well on a ben yomo, boiling it with something pogum in it, I don't know, it seems to make everything pogum in the walls of the pot even if you like the Badei Hashulchan. No, correct, no, you're yeah, you've dealt with a different you've dealt with a different shaila. One second, it's different it's different if... But it’s going to make it all pogum, isn’t that the point? Why we wait, it’s going to
make it all pogum, but I first of all it would be אין מבטלין איסור לכתחילה because it’s real traifus. Here with milk or meat, it’s chad b’heteira and chad b’heteira, but traifus in the pot is אין מבטלין איסור לכתחילה because it’s an issur inside the pot. The question is if it’s because if it’s traifus and it’s an issur, then an issur you couldn’t you couldn’t do this. You wait ad de’pugal because then it’s not there’s no ta’am anymore, because then it’s pugal. No, you still have to kasher it. Right, I’m saying that’s...
right, I’m saying you don’t have to kasher it, I’m saying I just don’t know I don’t know that you’d be able to, I don’t know, I don’t know, I’d have to think about it. Okay, I’m going to skip source 28, there’s a Shevet HaLevi about these different steam-jacketed kettles that I’m sure you can look in the notes and find all about later, it’s very fascinating, but let’s go to dishwashers. Okay. So very very common shaila regarding basar b’chalav and kashrus and things like that is dishwashers. So if you really want, they give
you a whole description in the notes about how dishwashers work, you know, you could also just plug in a GoPro and then from the inside of your own dishwasher. They also give you a video you can watch. There’s lots of good things. So what’s the shaila with the dishwasher? So is the dishwasher like your big vat of water in that what can I do? I could well let’s go opposite extremes. Could I put milchigs and fleishigs in there together because why?
Because it’s not mevatel issur lechatchila because there’s no issur. Do can we can we do that? Is the water that comes out first, is it cold, is it hot? What happens if there’s leftover food, if there’s not leftover food? We’re not going to talk here tonight about how well you clean off your dishes before you load the dishwasher, but that also might be something we’re going to mention. So let’s go to source 59, okay? It’s me or is it very hot in here? It’s me. It’s hot in here. Do we need
to does that work we have to like call Captain Z? Okay, fine. Veiter. Source 59, the Avnei Yashpei Rabbi Feinhandler says the following about a dishwasher. So he paskens that it’s assur to use a dishwasher for meat and then dairy. Okay, we’re not even talking about together, which we’ll talk about in a little bit. That for sure not together, but I cannot do milchigs, wait, and then do fleishigs. Why? ונראה פשוט שאם יש בהן ואינו בטל בשישים, if there’s mammash
food on there, הרי דאף נותן לו טעם. Everything is going to stick. כגון שכח בהן ונמצא שמדיח ומסיר חלבי that if it washed off my mac and cheese, ומבשל בו בשר אחר כך. That’s a problem. נמצא שהכלים והדפנות בלועים בשר וחלב. So if I did fleishig wash and I get meatballs in the walls of the pot, then I do my mac and cheese in there and then noodles and cheese went in there, now what do I have in the walls of the pot?
Now I have an issur. And then if I add more dishes later, I traif up all those dishes. Okay. So the Avnei Yashpei says that not only can you not do them together but for sure you can’t even do them one after the other. So if I ran a, you know, assur if I ran a fleishig wash and there’s no shishim, the dishwasher is going to be fleishig. He says emes. ממש רק מסוג אחר יש איסור כגון שממש של בשר בכלים שהדיח, if I washed off the meat keilim, and lo haya shishim, but there wasn't shishim,
there wasn't enough water to get all the food that I left on my plate, ושוב הדיח כלים חלביים נקיים and then I do ben yomo keilim after that. Ha-keilim v’ha-defanos, everything is assur mishum basar b’chalav. That’s mammash meforash lashon ha-Shulchan Aruch like the plate כקערה של בשר שהדיחה ביורה חלבית מותר. Okay, and he quotes the Rama that this is assur. We know the Rama forbids doing this, placing clean dairy dishes, right, clean dairy dishes in a fleishig pot with water.
Okay. If you go to the end, he says v’chen l’ma’aseh, so he concludes, לא נראה להתיר להשתמש במדיח אחד לבשרי ולחלבי. You cannot use it one for the other, it would be a problem, and therefore it would be assur. Okay. Fine, that is the consensus of many many poskim. In comes Rav Moshe. Is there some way to kasher a dishwasher? Ah, right. Kashering a dishwasher we’re going to talk about in a little bit. Kashering a dishwasher is a kashering shaila. You find different kashrus organizations have different opinions
about it. The general first of all not for Pesach because it’s almost impossible. There is there is like usually what happens if people move into a new place, if you can get new racks, if you get new if it’s metal inside you run it... once, but you should get new racks. If the racks are mamish new and they're metal, you can kasher them, but if not, you should try to get new racks. Okay. Are there other questions? There are times we allow, the OU allows kashering of the dishwashers, the CRC, there are times you have to be meikel because people they might need
it. But we try like it's not like you can use it Monday for milchigs, run it Tuesday and use it for fleishigs for Wednesday. But in comes Rav Moshe. Rav Moshe
paskins, no, you actually can use it for both. ודבר החדש לרחוץ את הכלים שנקרא בשם dishwasher אם יכול לרחוץ כלי בשר וכלי חלב זה אחר זה הנה צריך שמה שמניחים הכלים
שהוא לכלי בשר אחרים לכלי חלב אחרים. Says Rav Moshe, you can use the same dishwasher as long as you have separate racks. אבל לא כתבתי שם הטעם pashut, says Rav Moshe, I didn't really give the explanation over there in a different teshuva in חלק ד' יורה דעה דבעצם נט בר נט מותר. This is ממש נט בר נט. He quotes the Rama: דאפילו באותן מים שהודחו בהן כלי בשר, the water that washed fleishig kelim,
מותר להדיח גם כלי חלב. Why? Because it's nat bar nat and therefore, says Rav Moshe, that would be the same situation here. He says vechol shekein bekan. Not only that, it's even better. You're telling me I washed my meat dishes Monday morning. Okay. So the water washed it off and maybe it was nosein ta'am into the walls of the dishwasher. Now I have new water... when it was the same water, the Rama's
meikel. Now I have new water and new racks, so Rav Moshe says we should be meikel. There is questions on this Rav Moshe in terms of, like, how long? Do you have to wait 24 hours? But let's finish it. אבל מה שהמצאתי שם שמה שמניח הכלים צריך שיהיו אחרים. Why do I need something else? Why do I need racks then? דמטעם שמצוי שישאר דבר בעין. If something actual was mamashus, was actual food, that's going to be a problem. Where is that food? That food is not on the walls
of the dishwasher. Where is that food? It's on the racks. So the racks won't... if there's food, that's not going to help you. And therefore, says Rav Moshe, as long as you would have separate racks, it would potentially be okay. Now, you cannot use it if it was not kosher. If you traifed up or it was a non-kosher, that gets into the kashering shaila, because here though we're just talking about where I'm using it one for milchigs and one for fleishigs. What's the difference between being traif
and milchigs and fleishigs together? Would be traif also. It's not traif. It's not milchigs and... first of all, he didn't say milchigs and fleishigs together. But I'm saying if you're talking about traif, we kashered, the CRC over the years in hotels uses dishwashers in the hotels that are traif by running them, running hot water, running with soap, then running another hot water through the dishwasher, kashered even traif ones. So that's why I'm questioning this. These
are two separate things. You're talking about kashering a dishwasher. That we could talk about. Rav Moshe is saying if you have a non-kosher dishwasher, it doesn't work to just do this system of, like, if there's traifus. A non-kosher dishwasher, not traifed up dishwasher. Correct. Kashering dishwashers we could talk about. And he's saying they were treif because it's nat bar nat so you never have an actual issur hana'ah. Correct, correct. And that's why you need separate racks, because separate racks, the only time it would be a potential issue is when there's mamashus, that's only on the racks, that's not on the walls. How does it only go on the racks and not the walls? I don't get that. It all
mixes, how is it only on the racks and not the walls? No, no, no, no. He's saying the b'ayin. The reason I want racks, says Rav Moshe, is because if there's b'ayin, you have a problem. B'ayin doesn't work in nat bar... b'ayin is not nat bar nat. B'ayin is b'ayin. So therefore, get new racks, so therefore you have no problem with that. But the food literally stays on the racks and doesn't mix up? You're saying once it gets to the walls, it's already like got soap in it? No, no, no, no. If there's food left there, then it's going to become a problem. For... it's
nosein ta'am lifgam, then you're relying on lots of other heterim. Wait a second, one second, one second, one second. First of all, first of all, it's Rav Moshe Feinstein. So, okay, it's Rav Moshe Feinstein. They once brought Rav Shlomo Zalman ketchup and Rav Shlomo Zalman paskened a certain thing about ketchup because they brought him the wrong ketchup. This is Rav Moshe's pasken 50, 60 years ago about
dishwashers. Dishwashers have advanced, they've changed. Rav Moshe's psak in Chelek Alef of Orach Chaim and Chelek Beis of Yoreh Deah is you can use the dishwasher but you need separate racks. Why? Because he felt that
there is still be'ein left there. Even if there is not, it's a dangerous precedent to set. The only time that food might be left is on- I don't know about you, I've seen food in my dishwasher. Maybe I don't have a very good dishwasher. That's fine. You have a very- What? Are you saying that you're concerned that the food is absorbing directly from the walls? From a pagam standpoint? No, he's saying from a- I'm just confused about why- why separate racks and why not the walls or anything? He's concerned that the food, the food is sticking to the walls
with the wash it runs and then the same thing gets to the walls. No, no, no. One second. That's not an issue though. That's not an issue because I'm not using it together. If I was- We're going to talk about Rav Ovadia in a second. That's not an issue because it's then later it's not bar nat still. I ran it once, there might be be'ein in the walls of the pot- but it's fine because when the walls of the dishwasher- and I wash it again and it brings out that's not bar nat. Rav Moshe says it's- You can't apply nat bar nat if there's actual mamashut there. So mamashut he feels would be on the racks so he says to get separate racks.
Why is- Wait, why is the be'ein still the be'ein? Why is it not אינו ראוי לאכילת כלב? Why between the chemicals and the wash, don't you consider it food anymore? Because it was before the soap? First of all, you have to ask when it was nivlah. You don't know when it was nivlah. By the way, there's a shaileh in dishwashers. Some dishwashers they wash everything off in hot water first and then the soap comes out. So that's what we just said is a problem. We just said I can put afar in only beforehand. In most dishwashers, if you go inside, it's not what happens. Which is why
we're going to see that a lot of poskim are not meikel like this Rav Moshe. Okay. So if you look in Sefer- we're definitely not going to finish that- if you look in Source 61 in the Agur B'halacha, he quotes about- it's a good discussion. He says that Rav Moshe today would say differently. במדיחי כלים יש מקומות שנדבק שם ממשות חמץ או בשר וחלב ואי אפשר לנקותו רק על ידי אומן. There are certain places that they might go back and use it. ואין להביא ראיה מדברי הגאון באגרות משה. He says you cannot bring a raya from Rav Moshe Feinstein. Why? כי ישנם מינים ממינים
שונים ואולי באותו זמן לא היה חשש. This is a mefurash raya that you cannot pasken things just because you saw it in a teshuva of Rav Moshe Feinstein. Now I'm not saying Rav Moshe- we don't follow Rav Moshe, we are meikel like Rav Moshe sometimes, but sometimes a teshuva is what a teshuva is. It was written in whatever the generation, century was. You had to know what the situation was, all these different things. So says the Agur B'halacha, Rav Moshe would not allow it today, he would say assur. However, if you look in Source 62 in the Sheilos u'Tshuvos of the Shavei Tzion of הרב שמואל טוביה שטרן, he says the following. He says that no, actually he would allow a dishwasher for meat and
then dairy, it doesn't matter, and you actually don't have to change the racks in between. And he explains. He says- and the underline- ונת בר נת כזה לא גרע ממה שמשום שאין המים עושים פליטות ובלעיות הללו ובפרט שהמים אינו ככלי ראשון. He says the water being sprayed out is an iruy kli rishon
which can't really even remove anything from the walls of the thing. Iruy kli rishon isn't strong enough to take stuff out of the dishwasher and therefore he writes, לכן אני מסכים להתיר תשמיש מדיחי כלים הללו בזה אחר זה. So again, before we do one more, Dvar Yehoshua that says it's assur because it boley things. Rav Moshe says yes, but you do separate racks, I'm definitely okay with it because of nat bar nat. Agur B'halacha says though Rav Moshe
would not have said that today, Rav Moshe would have been machmir today because there's just so much happening in the dishwasher, it's too dangerous. And Shmuel Tuvia Stern says, what are you talking about? The fact that the water comes out first and it's only iruy kli rishon, I'm not worried about anything. You don't need separate racks. You can't do it together, but you don't need separate racks. In comes Rav Ovadia and Rav Ovadia says don't worry Sefardim. Don't worry Sefardim, I got this. Okay? Rav Ovadia in the Yabia Omer says the following. By the way, this is why I, you
know, you have to know how these things operate. Like for example, you know, whatever people do in their homes they do in their homes. But my Mesora from my Rebbe as much as I would like it not to be, is that not only do we not raise the oven on the Yom Tov on the Shabbos mode oven, but we do not use a warming drawer on Shabbos day. Okay? That's the Mesora I have from Rabbi Neuburger, in fact when he was by us for Shabbos, my wife tried once again. She said, just making sure nothing's changed Rebbe, and he said I
don't think so. But his point to me was you have to know how every warming drawer works. Okay? Everything operates differently and like when you talk to Poskim, you can't just Pasken, you have to like look at things change. How soap gets dispensed, when the water gets dispensed, how hot is the water, all of these things are parts of this. So let's go weiter very fast so we can move on a little bit. We got some interesting examples. The Yabia Omer in source 63 says Rav Ovadia both in 63 says מסקנא דדינא
יש להורות היתר מדיח כלים לכלי בשר וכלי חלב אפילו ביחד. Go ahead says Rav Ovadia. רק מהיות טוב היכא דאפשר להדיח כלי בשר לחוד וכלי חלב לחוד says Rav Ovadia it is better to use them separately but he would be okay if he used them together and he explains in source 64 in the Yalkut Yosef exactly what he said earlier that when the dishwasher spritzes out that water that's mixed with soap and then another it's all basically
there's nothing there is not enough food in there that would possibly that would trip up anything. So therefore he said it's really we are going you know there's room to be Meikel. But even Rav Ovadia, even the Sefardim they don't really really rely they generally try to do at least one after the other they don't really do milk and meat together. If you really like never cleaned off your plate, you like took your your plate of macaroni and cheese and your plate of meatballs and you put it in there, Rav Ovadia is not Meikel on that. Okay? But if it was washed off, Rav Ovadia would be Meikel.
But lemaisa lemaisa and he quotes that, you know, restaurants and things like that and hotels and things, that if the dishes don't have really large pieces it should be okay. All right. Aren't industrial dishwashers very different though than household ones? It could be, it could be. So you really have to you have to do each one. Okay. So, okay. Lemaisa lemaisa if you really do find like you know Pareve dishes and things like that and
you know a Pareve fork and usually we're Meikel about it, usually Meikel about it because of the soap and the hot water. If you don't really need it, the general Hakpada is to try and do Hagala if you could. You don't have to wait till Pesach. You could take a boiling pot of water, dunk it in, take it right out, obviously not with your hand. What? You wait 24 hours but velemaisa okay fine. And the He'arot in the notes I'll just share with you and because we discussed it in the past and we'll move on to source
65. That they quote here about the whole Dunkin Donuts Starbucks debate because this is where part of this gets played into it. And that we mentioned a while ago maybe a few weeks ago that when they wash everything together at Starbucks, so it's washed all of the things are washed together. So that includes the filters they're going to make your coffee with and that includes the thing they just made the ham and cheese sandwich with and they put it all in a bin and they wash it with boiling hot water and soap. So there that's the Chumra. And there's also a Chazon Ish that that's relied on that your
coffee thing that they're now going to make coffee for you for, you know, and that's why some of the CRC recommendation is the only thing that you can get is what's like free-standing and they it only goes like tea goes straight from the urn to the so it comes back to this issue that at a Starbucks it's a non-kosher restaurant that they're potentially washing all those together. Those that are Meikel on it are Meikel because there's sources to be Meikel on these things because we're not as Machmir when it's, you know, soap and Nosein Ta'am Lifgam and Nat bar Nat. But that is where the Chumra comes
in. As I mentioned they're not as Machmir when it comes to Dunkin Donuts because the dishes are not washed in such hot water. Okay. Gross but easier in Halacha. So anyway you can read it in the notes. It's interesting. If you really want to go down you can read all the CRC articles and Fishbane, all the different things but let's let's move on. Okay. Good we got a few minutes. Source 65. Source 65. Okay. So this is, you know, an interesting source for why we
generally try to leave things on separate parts of our counter. Okay? Even if you don't have a Milchig side and a Fleishig side but that it shouldn't be put down on the same counters together comes from the following Gemara. So the Gemara in Chulin says the following. בעי מיניה רב דימי מרב נחמן מהו להניחי כדא דמילחא could I... If I could if I could take a salt and put it Gabei Kadda De'Kamcha, which is like this kuthach? So could I put a salt, a salt, straight up salt next to this kuthach, this dairy dish? Because some
kuthach might fall in the salt, I might use that salt for meat and it might be a problem. So the Gemara says, Assur. Okay. The Gemara continues, De'Chala Mai? What about vinegar? Could I put kuthach next to vinegar? So the Gemara says, Amar Lei Shari. Yeah, you're okay. U'mai Shna? So why? So the Gemara says: דלמא אקרא דמלחא מאי טעמא, the Gemara has like a line like, figure this out: האי איתיה איסורא בעיניה והאי ליתיה איסורא בעיניה.
So the Gemara says that in vinegar and salt, you it's going to be mivattel, that if a little bit of that salt falls in the vinegar, sorry, a little bit of the vinegar falls in the salt, it's mivattel, but with the kuthach it clumps together and it's still like be'ayin like it's not going to be mivattel. Okay, fine. The what? Okay. The Shulchan Aruch in Siff Hey. So go to the Shulchan Aruch in Siff Hey. Shulchan Aruch in Siff
Hey says exactly what we saw in this Gemara. The Gemara says, the Shulchan Aruch says: אין מניחין כלי שיש בו כותח אצל כלי שיש בו מלח אבל מותר להניחו אצל כלי שיש בו חומץ. Exactly what we just said. The Rema adds: ודווקא עם הכלים מגולים. This is only if what? They're all uncovered. דאילו העביר ונתן ביחד, but if there was mixed dancing, mutter, it's mutter
for a minute if it was by accident. ולא חיישינן שמא נפל על המלח. We're not worried that like something happened. But in general, one thing should not be put next to the other thing. Like the Gra explains like it's not machzikin issura, but we're not really worried something happened, but generally keep the salt away from the kuthach, but the vinegar would would be okay. Fine. The Shulchan Aruch in Siff Vav says the following, based on a Tosfos in the Gemara that we just saw: מותר ליתן
בתוך תיבה כד של בשר אצל כד של חלב. What could I do? That I could place a jug of milk next to a jug of meat. Says the Shach in Siff Katan Chaf-Gimel, why is that okay? That sounds like blasphemy. It sounds like, kick that guy out of Semicha, Chaver. He says the Shach, demizar zahiri, I'm going to be very careful, שלא יפול מזה לזה, I'm going to be very careful. מה שאין כן בסיף ה דלא מסיק אדעתיה
שלא יפול מן הכותח, but this I'm going to be very, very, very careful. Okay? And the Shach clarifies in Siff Dalet, megullim only if it's really, really, you know, uncovered, but if it was covered, everything would be okay. So if you look in the Badei HaShulchan in source 66, says the Badei HaShulchan, this is why, this is why we have the following. Or this is also like a good idea like if you if
you have at your house, you know, I don't know, you have guests that are coming. So you make a whole, you know, the rest of the year you don't have a coffee station, but you make a coffee station, and you put coffees out, you put some sugar out in a bowl. Okay? So if that's a real coffee station, you should not take that sugar and then the guests leave, you're like, we're not fancy anymore, take that sugar and put it back in the thing and then use it for, you know, for baking or for cooking or for meat, it's going to be a problem. That has to be a creamer. Because that has to be a creamer after some problem.
I don't understand you. Best friend? I don't I don't yeah, I don't understand you. Yeah but you keep the creamer and the milk in the fridge where it's cold, and not on the counter where it's not. No, but still it potentially could still be an issue. Meaning if people brought creamer out there, it would still be an issue, I would think. I don't understand that either. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Okay. So yeah, and don't don't get me started, did you try the Trader Joe's one? Yeah, I did.
Tastes like every other one. Says the Badei HaShulchan: Vechatav od Maharshal. So the Maharshal explains: שהעולם נזהרים שלא להניח קדירה חולבת במקום שהניחו שם מקודם קדירת בשר. That the, you know, as they say in the Yeshiva world, the Velt is noheig that we don't put down the meat pot where or the milchig pot where the meat pot was. Why? דיש לחוש שנתשפך שם מתחילה ממאכל
של בשר ושוב נבלע לקדירה החולבת. Meaning if we're not so careful, this is not like at oh my gosh, this is a crazy situation, things spill all the time. If you making soup and you have hot soup and a little bit spilled on the counter. and then you bring over your mac and cheese pot and put it down, that's a big issue. That potentially could be a problem. Now, yeah, there might be shishim, there'd be lots of things. But therefore says the Badei Hashulchan, ואף על פי שצונן לא בלע אפילו הכי החמיר בדבר שלפעמים הקדירה חמה ולא אדעתיה ויש ליזהר בזה וכיוצא בזה
נתנו חכמים מקום בתוך המקרר לאחד משל חלב ומקום לעצמו לשל בשר. We should have separate places, separate counters, where, you know, where things are not going to touch one another. And if you have like a parve counter, it is really recommended that if you ever put something on a parve counter that's milk or meat, you should put a towel underneath it. It's just not worth it. You know, it wasn't dirty, I checked. Most of the time it should be fine. You
know, my wife is very makpid about this. I, you know, I try to- I don't want to show her the Badei Hashulchan. But it's something that we should try to be careful for. Fine. That is Sif Dalet, one more minute, perfect. If you look in Sif Zayin, Shulchan Aruch paskens that מלח הנתן בקערה של בשר, if I put meat, I'm sorry, if I had salt that was placed on fleishig dishes, I could actually use that meat- that salt for milchig. But says the Rema, anu machmirim,
tavo alav beracha, כי יש מחמירים לכתחילה. That we should really be machmir on this. The Taz disagrees and says why are you machmir on this? The Badei Hashulchan, Sif Katan 67, defends the Rema and explains the Rema was being machmir only in a situation where that fleishig pot had a little like layer of something, and I'm nervous that like the salt absorbed- like, if you had a fleishig bowl that you hadn't used in three days and was completely clean and not hot, and you accidentally dumped
salt in there, you could take out that salt, put it into milk and drink it. But the Rema is being machmir because if you had a kli that was dirty, you might not realize, it's just better to be machmir, right? Better to be machmir. Alright, good, shkoyach. So next week, the one minute, perfect.